<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brefe declaration of the great, and innumerable myseries [and] wretchednesses vsed i[n] courte tyall, made by a lettre, whych mayster Alayn Charatre wrote to hys brother, which desyred to come dwel in the court, for to aduyse, [and] counsell hym not to enter into it, lest he after repe[n]t, newly augme[n]ted, amplified, [and] inrytched, by Francis Segar.</title>
            <title>Curial. English</title>
            <author>Chartier, Alain, 15th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1549</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18508</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5058</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109737</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845383</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845383</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10280</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18508)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10280)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 61:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brefe declaration of the great, and innumerable myseries [and] wretchednesses vsed i[n] courte tyall, made by a lettre, whych mayster Alayn Charatre wrote to hys brother, which desyred to come dwel in the court, for to aduyse, [and] counsell hym not to enter into it, lest he after repe[n]t, newly augme[n]ted, amplified, [and] inrytched, by Francis Segar.</title>
                  <title>Curial. English</title>
                  <author>Chartier, Alain, 15th cent.</author>
                  <author>F. S. (Francis Segar), fl. 1549-1563.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4+] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>J. Day and W. Seres?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1549.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Chartier, Alain.  Le curial.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; a fragment.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Courts and courtiers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  Social life and customs --  1328-1600 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10280:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 4 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:10280:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 4 -->
            <p>¶ A Brefe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the great / and innumerable myſeries / &amp; wretchedneſſes vſed i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> courtes ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, made by a lettre, whych may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Alayn Charatre wrote to hys brother, which deſyred to come dwel in the court, for to aduyſe, &amp; counſell hym not to enter into it, leſt he after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, newly aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, &amp; inryt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched, By Francis Segar.</p>
            <p>1549</p>
            <q>
               <l>He that doth couyt the courtly lyfe to know</l>
               <l>Yf it wyl pleaſe him, to take a lyttle payne</l>
               <l>To rede this treatyſe, whych here doth folow</l>
               <l>Wherin it is diſcrybed, brefely, and playn.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:10280:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->
            <head>¶ F.S. to the reader.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Here haſt thou expreſſed before thy eyſe</l>
               <l>The myſery and wretchednes of the lyfe curial</l>
               <l>And howe that by fortune ſome dayly do ryſe.</l>
               <l>And contrary wyſe by hee agean do fall,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Truſt not to fortune which alway is variable</l>
               <l>For ſome ſhe doth exalt &amp; ſome ſhe bringeth low</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he is neuer true, conſtant and ſta<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le</l>
               <l>But as tydes vſe theyr tymes, to ebbe &amp; to flow</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Couetouſnes cauſeth myſchefe to ryſe</l>
               <l>Deſyre of dignite with pompous ambition</l>
               <l>Which the wyſe man, doth alwaye diſpyſe</l>
               <l>And is content, wyth hys vocation</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> froward fortune, with frownyng face</l>
               <l>At your inhauncinge, taketh grudge or enuy</l>
               <l>In ſhort tyme, ſhe wyl you diſplace</l>
               <l>And bring you to ſhame ruen and myſery</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <unclear>Ill</unclear> you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ar called, vnto any hygh place</l>
               <l>Be true vnto your, anoynted Kynge</l>
               <l>And call vnto God, to geue you the grace</l>
               <l>So to contynu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, to your lyues endynge,</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="fragmentary_text">
            <pb facs="tcp:10280:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->
            <p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap> court, that they that be ſymple, be diſprayſed, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertuous enuyed, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proud arrogau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, in mortal pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryl. And yf thou be placed vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other courchiers, thou ſhalt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy at theyr power, yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> be in mean eſtate, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which thou haſt not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fiſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, thou ſhalt labour &amp; ſtriue for to mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te &amp; ryſe hyer, &amp; yf thou mayſt come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hye ſecretes whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che be ſtrongly to doubte, feare, &amp; drede, in the doubtous courteyns of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt hie pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> be moſt infortunate, for ſo moch as y<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt to be moſt fortunate &amp; hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>py, ſo moch more ſhalt thou be in great dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger &amp; peril to fal, like to him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is mounted into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt hys place, for to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fortune y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riable hath moſt hyghly lyfte vp, and inhau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed, reſteth nomore, but for to falle fro ſo hye, downe, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe oweth to them, nothyng but ſhame, ruine, and deſtruction yf that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt taken of her al that
<pb facs="tcp:10280:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->thou myghteſte, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe woulde geue, then arte thou detter of thy ſelfe, to the ende that ſhe render &amp; yelde y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> infortunate, and vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe hadde before inhaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe mocke hym of hys miſchefe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe had made blind of vayn glory of hys inhaunſyng for the great wyndes that blowe in hye courtes, be of ſoche nature, and condicion, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they only that be hygheſt inhaunſed, be after theyr diſpoyntmente / as a ſpectacle of enuy, detractyon or of hate, vnto all people, and fynd them ſelf, ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iectes, tyl they be ſhamed and put down amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the people, and that they that before ſiewed to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and flattered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reporte of them more greater blames and deuyſyons, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other, for the multitude of people diſprayſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alway y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune hath moſt altered, &amp; throwen down, and alſo is enuious at the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10280:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
